this is a continuation
of my
so so i'll just
recap and continue sort of where we left
off
again the buddha is just this is a
teaching uh where he's teaching us how to
uh where he's teaching us how to
restrain
the artifacts and how to abandon the
artists the defilements so to
and he began by saying that the
destruction of these
archivers these defilements is for one
who knows and sees
for one who knows and sees attention
with perspective
or attention without and
what is attention without perspective so
he knows the difference
and then we went to the the first way to
abandon these defilements is by seeing
and the pali word is dasana so
defilements to be abandoned by dasana
so i looked it up and it's like
it seems to suggest that the word app
perception is a good translation for that seeing
is a good translation for that seeing
our perception
but observing things and then over time
seeing where they rooted your actions
and you were saying the other day that
this practice is basically about
changing the significance
of the thing well yeah yeah
well our perception is is that like
through through the experience of
certain perceptions you you get to
get to understand more so next time you
perceive the same thing you don't have
to go through the same motions of
recollecting what you understood
understanding knowledge
becomes part of now that perception
becomes the significance of what you're
seeing so you're not perceiving your knowledge
so you're not perceiving your knowledge
directly like it's not written in this
thing but because of the effort you made
the knowledge now becomes the
significance of your perception
that's what the buddha said the
knowledge uh
is the result of perception perception
comes first having perceived one then
gets to develop knowledge about it
but once you know it you don't need to
keep telling yourself oh
let me now get the knowledge of this
which i'm perceiving because perceiving
it
will mean that knowledge is present so
that's well that's how i understand our
well that's how i understand our
perception as
a term so and yeah that knowledge is on
the level of changing the significance
of things so
seeing a beautiful object for a mind
that's not
trained uh results in basically
significance of centrality significance
of all gratification of my pleasure
joy i can get if i have this beautiful
object fear of losing the beautiful object you
fear of losing the beautiful object you
might have to protect it all that is
significance of seeing the beautiful
object but if you've been practicing sensory
but if you've been practicing sensory
strain long enough understanding dumb
sufficiently enough developing
mindfulness to the extent necessary
perception of beautiful will be
signifying danger
will be signifying pedal like the buddha
said uh
like like um was it the
the pit filled with burning embers
charcoal yeah charcoal filled with
burning embers
and uh that's the same sensuality now
the man sees it he sees for what it is
and if somebody if two strong men will
come and pick you up and
carry you to throw you in a charcoal pit
like your intention would be everywhere
else you would want to be anywhere else
you would want to be anywhere else
except there you wouldn't want to go
into the
pit of burning embers so that's how the
significance of sensuality must be developed in order
of sensuality must be developed in order
for you to abandon centrality you need
to start seeing it
as a charcoal pit full of burning embers
so the mind will completely
completely not want to even entertain it
for a split second so to speak
so if you cultivate that sufficiently
enough because
sensuality is factually charcoal pet
with burning embers
they will become apparent and it's like
the danger became apparent the escape
became apparent and all these things
that we talked about so the next time you see
we talked about so the next time you see
a central thing
that's that our perception you're not
perceiving they're beautiful anymore
it's still the same thing you're
perceiving by the way
but now your perception with that
knowledge is seeing the danger and the
ugly you you have changed the significance of
you you have changed the significance of
that
perception you've undone yeah that those
significances of exactly because those significances
of exactly because those significances
were not set in stone if there were
freedom from sunshine they would not be
possible they were simply maintained
through your perpetual engagement
careless engagement
and ignorant engagement with desire and
sense gratification
so you you kind of start off
obviously full of lust and ignorance
yeah and seeing your body as a
wonderful thing and as a tool of getting
more wonderful things
but then you need to the practice is to
re-signify it or take apart that
significance there by looking
at it for what it is well exactly and in
order for you to start seeing it for
what it is you need to start restraining
your body first
so you're still regarding centrality as
beautiful so that's like that's one layer so to
so that's like that's one layer so to
speak but then
acting out of body towards more
gratification essentiality seeking more
essential object
that's another layer you add on top of
the layer of your thought
so you're heading so as long as any of
those layers are there
you are fueling that misperception that
wrong significance the mistaken notion
of centrality is beautiful
and uh non-harmful so you need to first
start restraining the coarser layer
which is layer of physical action even
if you mentally still don't see a reason
for it
and you're still attracted to it and you
still don't see it as dangerous or
perilous you need to restrain your body first
you need to restrain your body first
pretty much out of faith
initially until you get understanding
for yourself and then you're the same
like we said that many times before you come
we said that many times before you come
with a horrible skin disease
it itches like hell you go to see the
doctor the doctor gives the medicine but
says well before you start
start applying the medicine you need to
stop scratching it
because doesn't matter the amount of
medicine you apply the amount of your
meditation you do and soot as you read
if you keep scratching your itch you are
aggravating your condition
so he doesn't know that the doctor's
medicine will help him the only way to
find out
is first out of faith taking the trust
that he should stop scratching
well let's see yeah he has to take on
faith that the doctor is right and that that
that the doctor is right and that that
scratching is the wrong thing to do so
he's got to keep telling himself in a
way she really believes the doctor oh this
she really believes the doctor oh this
scratching is bad
rather than the scratching is good for
me yeah yeah yeah
so yeah so that's like you take this
yeah exactly you start rewriting the
significance you take basically you take an external
you take basically you take an external
view out of faith
and obviously some consideration you
don't want to just be faithful you want
to consider it as we said before
and then just blindly take it but think
about it
reason and see which is least likely to
be wrong is this doctor
is there a good chance that he might be
right what do i have to lose either way
so it's not like how you follow this
teacher to the end of the world and like
for the rest of your life no you take on
his instruction
until you're killed and then you won't
need to have faith in him because
you're cured so you know that he was
right he's not for faith now he's just
confidence that
what you did on the kind of that
instruction was correct
but even then so you have to take it
externally because your whole condition is affected
because your whole condition is affected
with the disease so to speak
so you have no health reference point
since you can remember your skin was
itching so you take it on trust externally
so you take it on trust externally
external point of view saying actually
if you stop scratching sufficiently
enough the time will come when you will
heal now you value the pros the idea of
now you value the pros the idea of
healing after
you know thinking about it so you take
it and trust
so whichever view you take control is
basically like like grafting a tree
you take a completely different thing
and then you put it onto this tree
and if you cultivate it rightly enough
it will grow into the tree and then it
will become a new tree
that's like how the grafting is done so
then you have the mix of the previous
and and and the new tree so to speak so the
and and the new tree so to speak so the
you have to graft the view onto your
experience they will then take over things because
they will then take over things because
they would if the view was right that
you took if the
instruction was for from the buddha for
example and you took it rightly and
you've been restrained
it will have to take like it will have
to start growing correctly
because the view was right and that
means it corresponds to the universal
nature of things
such as sensuality was truly unpleasant
it was truly burning
embers he was truly dissatisfactory
and you took that on trust and then kept
applying it and kept applying it and
keeping the basis of restraint
and then it took root because those were
the exactly matching conditions for the
view that you took
so that's same so you take the you take
the medicine you follow the doctor's
instruction if it doesn't work well you review it is
if it doesn't work well you review it is
it because i'm not restrained enough
honestly speaking or is it because no
i'm completely restrained i'm doing
completely restrained i'm doing
everything rightly but this doesn't seem
to be curing me of my
itch so maybe i should look for another
doctor and then do the same so you do want
and then do the same so you do want
results
don't just take it in faith without any
results whatsoever
but then at the same time don't forget
that you don't really
uh know what right results are at that
stage so there has to be some time
involved on during which you're applying these
on during which you're applying these
things out of faith and confidence that
it will help you it can't happen
overnight
yeah it takes
so just to recap again
these defilements to be abandoned by
scene by a perception
so says that's an ordinary person
does not understand what things are fit
for attention and what things are unfit
for attention
since that is so he attends to things
that are unfit for attention
and he does not attend to those things
fit for attention
and what are the things unfit for
attention that he attends to
they are things such that when he
attends to them the unarisen
defilement of sensual desire arises
the defilement of being arises
and the defilement of ignorance arises
or increases
it increases yeah so
he doesn't see what the
you know what he's attending to he's
actually causing him
his problems the way he's attending to
things is making defilements worse
increasing them sustaining them
maintaining them
but the noble disciple because he
attends to things with
a perspective he can see ah this
is suitable this thing that i tend to
now which is kind of
uh neutral maybe in itself is actually
increasing my
essential design then you realize it's
not neutral
okay
so so the noble disciple then has this
ability to see his mind and to see the
defilements that are in his mind and the
rising increasing or decreasing wow think about
increasing or decreasing wow think about
it in the same simile
of the skin condition and the medicine
from the doctor in the beginning
all you know is itch you don't really
know what's helpful what's not helpful
so you start restraining you start
putting this cream on you start not
exposing it to sun
cleaning your wound as the woody would
say and so on
and then it starts getting better
so now you do recognize improvement for
yourself which means you don't need to keep
which means you don't need to keep
reminding yourself of the faith you have
in a doctor because it's working
but you're still not fully healed
so that that would be the equivalent of
a noble disciple
so from the point of view of partially
healed wound and diminished itch
he knows exactly now because that's now
his criteria
oh actually this is now bringing back
that old ditch that
was gone it disappeared but if i do this
that it's making it even less richer
than before so it's healing more
or aggravating it again and now he can
know because he gained some perspective
due to the actual
healing of his skin condition
so that's why the noble disciple would
know what's fit for attention but it
isn't because he actually
sees it oh if i attend to this that
which hasn't healed yet
is not gonna heal if i attend to this
that which hasn't healed yet is healing more
more
but it but also ordinary people can sort
of
can practice that you can see well well
you could you should be trying yeah
i'm doing these actions and what is the
result of it more central design
more you know distractions you won't
have you won't have a a petuna
you won't have a a petuna
can by all means and should by all means
be trying to emulate
sort of or higher because that's how you
have a chance of understanding it
but don't confuse yourself into like
believing that you are now because look
i'm doing it
so what what boutum will not have is the
immediacy of that criteria that a noble disciple
of that criteria that a noble disciple
has
he immediately knows he might choose to
ignore it but it's invisible
for him it's immediately visible whether
this is suitable or unsuitable
right how unsuitable this is or how
suitable this is
that doesn't have that he doesn't have
the immediacy of that criteria
which means he needs to invest more
effort like wider effort
into constantly recollecting the context
of the danger that he took on faith
the context of avoiding this cultivating
that what doctor told him he needs to keep
what doctor told him he needs to keep
more in his mind because he doesn't have
the immediate verification that oh look
my wounds getting better
my wounds getting worse for him it all
works he's suffering yeah so he has no no no
he's suffering yeah so he has no no no
criteria that will come internally from
the wound
it's all like what he has adopted as as
views and faith
but that's what i mean like as i said
noble zebra doesn't need to remind
himself anymore that the doctor knows what he's
anymore that the doctor knows what he's
talking about because
he's wound he's that's the significance
of his wound now healing wound
is basically the significance of a
doctor was correct
yeah now he has got a criteria he knows
what healing is he sees it he sees now so
healing is he sees it he sees now so
now he can pick up the sign of
unwholesome exact wholesome
immediately in in anything that he
attends
and by seeing that this is increasing
defilements he doesn't attend to it he doesn't go in
he doesn't attend to it he doesn't go in
that direction
he chooses the other way but he abandons
the defilements because of that exactly
that direct seeing is the direct feedback
and anyway it here it says that th these
three are servers
these three defaults sensual desire
being an
ignorance and just
being the defilement of being
maybe we can briefly say what well
didn't we do the whole talk on that
beings yeah being
existent so any so i want to get into
that now because that is
we did a whole talk on that
but anything that increases being yeah
ignorance yeah so it's basically being is what you
yeah so it's basically being is what you
have left
after you abandon centrality these are
the three types of being
the central being the the material being
and the immaterial being
when there is a central being being is
there because that's the coarsest type of
because that's the coarsest type of
being it's not only when you engage it
so if you're not free from centrality
you're always
your being is on the plane of centrality
on the plane of the senses
now if you have abandoned centrality
then your being is on the plane of the
presence of the form
then if you abandon that then your being
is on the level of the absence of the
form and so on but now that's just way
too abstract for any practical
application for somebody who be
listening to his talk
so practically speaking whatever your
current situation is
means it exists it's present there's
such it has appeared it means being is
there if you're not an arahant means there is
if you're not an arahant means there is
a degree of being
and being means misconception in that
sense being is unwholesome
i am yeah exactly so whenever there is a
being there is appropriation whenever there is
there is appropriation whenever there is
a being there is a sense of self
whenever there is a being there is a
sense of i
am right and vice versa whenever the
sense of i am means there is a degree of
being there
but it's and this is saying that the
noble disciples sees he would seize what
will increase that and what wouldn't
increase that
yeah i think i think it's it's a bit
cause to say
oh sense of self is what the being is
but practically speaking it is
there is no sense of being or existence
that you can perceive
apart from your sense of self so even in
philosophy people think they're talking
about the pure being
independent of the individual that's a
pure abstraction that's within
their sense of self and being of it
so being bava existence in philosophy
whatever you want to call it whichever
word you want to use
if you are honestly and like strictly
looking at it as a phenomena it's
inseparable from the sense of self and
your current situation
that's why your current situation will
either be on the level of kamababa
rupavava or arupa depending on how much
effort you you made to abandon it
so yes practically speaking being baba
is that being of i am even if you don't
explicitly think in terms of yourself
the fact
is that your point of view already
carries a degree of that
self-centeredness and and conceiving of i am that being is
and and conceiving of i am that being is
there
so it's subtler than i am such and such
but it's a kind of root of it anyway
so if you want to practically start
thinking about being and
trying to get a criteria what would
increase the being what would decrease
the being
think from that oh the self-centeredness
the conceit the i
am the self the the the point of view
right so just end up reflecting
on well exactly will this like again
is this is this pleasing to me is this
displeasing to me
why does that matter to me
because in a way you realize that many
on many instances you operate
like throughout your life just out of
these um things that infer
um things that infer
from the sense of self to me and for me
he's like here but do they ever stop and
think why why is this a problem for me
or why
do i want this no it just happened that
my sense of self wanted this
that was providing me with gratification
and i never questioned it
so stop using your sense of self as a
reference point
means to some extent you're already
shifting away from that like
uh perpetuating that being with that
wrong view
and the ultimate being that there is a
use as a reference point
is centrality that's the first and
foremost for most people
like pleasure pain that's the criteria
that's literally the the
the place the self-centered kind of the
center from which they infer
whether something is worth doing or not
we're doing will this provide me with
pleasure or will this punish me with
pain but so if if you stop using that center
but so if if you stop using that center
you stop relying on kamababa you stop
relying on the central being
and instead maybe you inform your
perspective a bit more
and you say well sense restraint will
hurt me
initially but you know if it's to
believe all these wise men and even my
own reasoning
i think there is a chance that he might
heal my my wound of central
itch and so on so immediately you're
choosing pain
pretty much which is against the
criteria of your karma power and what
you are basically
but so see you're not using that
self-centered being
of karma sensuality as a reference point
anymore but are actually dissolving it into
but are actually dissolving it into
something more wholesome something more
informed
and if you abandon sensuality you have
abandoned kamabala so you're being
baba has diminished to great extent now
there are subtle forms of baba but again
you're unable to think about satter
forms of baba
unless you're already free from
kamaballa because whenever you think
about all sorts of types of bhava you're
thinking it through the framework obama
that you are
which is for most people karma because
most people are not free from sensuality
even the lower noble disciples are not
free from sexuality so they are not free
from that
from that baba yet okay
okay
again it says uh the ordinary person
this is how he attends unwisely or
without without perspective yeah he
without perspective yeah he
what he asks questions internally so to
speak was i in the was i in the past was i not
was i in the was i in the past was i not
in the past
having been what did i become in the
past what shall i be in the future
have been having been what shall i
become in the future
or else he is inwardly perplexed about
the present
thus am i am i not what am i how am i
where has this been come from where will
it go there's a few more
sure so that's what i was saying see in
that instance
just just clearly shows how not just
that you're not free from the gratuitous
self-centered sense of i am i am the
center of the world heck
like was i in the past like everything
is determined by
you and whether you were and will you
and uh like are you going to be
that's already completely gratuitous
but so even if you don't necessarily act
out of that wrongly assumed center of sense
of that wrongly assumed center of sense
of self
entertaining these questions still
perpetuates the centeredness
of that gratuitous view that's where
those are wrong questions as the buddha
would say
no because oh you know you can never
express what the true selfie no
it's simply because any of those
questions still revolves around the
assumption that that self is in the
center and it's worth answering self-centered questioning
self-centered questioning
so am i in the past was was in the past
will it be in the future
takes for granted that that self is the
center of that
whole experience and thus it's important
for me to know whether in the past and
will be in the future but that's actually
be in the future but that's actually
relevant
what is relevant is to stop being
centered upon that
self-centered so mindfulness is already
a way
of of of cultivating or maintaining
or preventing yourself from becoming
reabsorbed uh too deeply into that gratuitously
uh too deeply into that gratuitously
assumed self-centered i am
that just basically always serves its
own purpose so
you live the noble disciple lives
according to
uh the nature of things exactly rather
than the nature of himself yeah so as it says
the nature of himself yeah so as it says
this is how he attends without
perspective so he this
ordinary person doesn't have that
perspective of the nature of things yeah
and thus he thinks he's the center he's
the yeah that's that's implicit
that's part of the significance he
doesn't even need to think it he needs
to actively think the opposite
to eventually undo that significance one
could do so the buddha says this
yet i'm doing this yeah so let me have
faith and do what he says
not what i put myself second and that's
why faith as blind as it is always
faith as blind as it is always
in its nature can be a factor that can
uh that can help somebody with the right
view not in itself but exactly if somebody
not in itself but exactly if somebody
out of faith
firm faith decides to use buddha's
reference point
from the suttas and not his reference
point so
i want to do this the buddha say you
shouldn't do it and i don't do it
and you stick to it it's going to take
longer than if you make more active
effort in terms of a persona but nevertheless
in terms of a persona but nevertheless
you are doing the work that's where
there is a
the southern usari type they want
through faith
adopts certain behavior and sticks to it
and it goes against his entire grain of
his being
but he sticks to it and that being will
evaporate sufficiently and then he
becomes sudapane like sada nussari
that leads to the right view
so yes whether you and whether and for
most people will be a combination a bit
of everything
like some stuff taken on faith some
stuff taken on
upon your own reasoning basically
anything any little helps and you would
be taking
whichever any help you can get because
as we've said in the past what i've seen
in the past
in the suitors it's clear like sexual
sexual activity needs to be abandoned
it's unwholesome the buddha says it for
the practice of dhamma yes you cannot
have it
yet for many people yeah but well you
know yeah
you know you know well it's a case means
they don't have enough faith
yeah because if they did they wouldn't
even need to reason
i mean some people need to reason but i
personally need to reason or need it to
reason things
faith wasn't really working so that's to
that extent
whichever way it is you do need to start
emulating that behavior
either a kind of faith or an account of
your reasoning but you need to start
doing it
not like oh i have faith the good is the
greatest but
does your behavior emulate what the
great buddha said
or not or like yes i have reasoned
everything the buddha is perfectly right
again does your behavior emulate now that
does your behavior emulate now that
rightness that you reasoned
no well you will not bear the results
it's again like the similar bully gave
like a
a hand that sits on her eggs even if she
doesn't wish for the chicks to pierce
she is making the effort doing the work
and sitting on her eggs they will
come out safely and be born into this
world alternatively have the hand that doesn't
alternatively have the hand that doesn't
sit on her eggs doesn't do the work
but she wishes that her checks come out
in this world they want
wishing is irrelevant whether you wish
or not
it's basically whether you do it or not
that's going to bear the results
and they would have said that the dharma
and the practice and the results of them
are not to be obtained by the wishing
alone like you can wish and because of the
like you can wish and because of the
wish you start making the effort
and sit on the eggs until they hatch but
if you just wish and glorify your wish
as most people's faith practice these
days is you're not doing the work
is that oh i'm so devote devoted i i'm
i'm so proud i'm so happy i'm so
inspired do you keep the five receipts do you
do you keep the five receipts do you
keep the eight precepts how you
celebrate do it once a day
how much time do you spend in solitude
do you read the suitors oh
no no no no no because i have such a
great faith well that faith is
meaningless it's like
i have a faith in this doctor oh but i'm
not neither abstaining from
from scratching neither covering it from
the sun
neither cleaning it from the dust
neither applying the medicine
i just have a shrine that venerated this
great doctor
and it's like okay so you cannot
possibly expect to heal but it just reminds me
expect to heal but it just reminds me
also the
the person with faith real faith
proper faith he he he takes on it he has
that idea
the buddha is the teacher i am the
disciple yeah isn't it
it's one of those suitors yeah yeah yeah
he knows what he's taught i do not i do
not know
even though i i believe this way
but he's saying to go this way well
things
so again just to continue on that
ordinary person when he attends
without perspective one of six
views arise in him
the self exists for me
no self exists for me i perceive self
with self i believe not self self
i perceive self with not self
it is this self of mine that speaks and
feels and experiences here and now the
results of good and bad actions
but this self of mine is permanent
everlasting eternal
not subject to change and it will endure
as long as eternity
well all of that is on the level of
significance of your experience of your self-centered
of your experience of your self-centered
experience those are not explicit
thought that people will have in them i
will live forever nobody thinks that
yet everybody is a victim of their view
unless you're a sodopan
so that's what you need to understand
when you read these sutras it's like
it's going to make
sense okay okay but there's like yeah
but i don't partake on this level
this is for somebody who already
understood and he's describing how when
you boil down things how they're seen
practically speaking you don't see that
you are a victim already
off your own delusion of your own
ignorance so practically speaking
if you want to understand these six
basically products you should see that
what do they all have together in common
is that self
it's basically not a problem but the
result of a problem
your sense of self is a symptom so it's
a symptom of you your itch
is a symptom of your skin condition in
itself it's not the issue
because you can itch and scratch and so
on but unless you uproot the underlying
cause you're still under the same condition
you're still under the same condition
so the sense of self i am i'm not will i
be
all of that is already the result of
that self-centeredness that we mentioned
before and that's where the problem is only
and that's where the problem is only
seeing or basically
mostly seeing things through your own
point of view that's fueled by greed
aversion delusion
seeking the pleasure avoiding pain and
distracting yourself from neutral
that's why sense restraint um like
virtue and sense restraint is already
kind of forcing you to go against the
grain of
your sense of self that's why it's
actually psychologically frightening
for people to to to like even if they're
not celibate just the idea of celibacy
or the idea of not scratching their it
freaks them out
well that's like too much pain to bear
because their sense of self is so
dependent upon those outlets
but if you actually start practicing
that you are already undermining that
gratuitous self-centeredness so your
sense of self is diminishing even if you
don't necessarily
you know measure it or you can quantify
it or
so it's not about finding the answer to
what myself and this myself
it's about uprooting things sufficiently
enough until those six
types of perceiving it are dissolved and
then you know
and then what's left is with not self
you see not self